<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Azure and DevOops</title>
    <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Azure and DevOops</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Christian Piet (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 10:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://manbearpiet.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Speeding up GitHub Workflow Federated authentication to the Azure Platform</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/githublogonazure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/githublogonazure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we were running into issues because our pipelines in GitHub Actions were taking too long to authenticate to the Azure platform using the &lt;code&gt;azure/login&lt;/code&gt; action with federated credentials. Initially it took around 25-30 seconds to authenticate, but over time this increased to over 3-4 minutes, which is not acceptable in our CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So I decided to investigate the issue and found a workaround that significantly speeds up the authentication process.&#xA;In this blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share how I managed to reduce the authentication time from several minutes to just a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Other Neovim editing basics</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;searching-replacing-and-commenting-in-neovim&#34;&gt;Searching, replacing, and commenting in Neovim&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my previous posts, I covered the basics of navigating Neovim and editing text. While moving around words, lines, or paragraphs in &lt;code&gt;Normal&lt;/code&gt; mode and selecting text with &lt;code&gt;Visual&lt;/code&gt; mode, it works swiftly to navigate around text; sometimes, you need to look for something specific one or multiple times. In this post, I will cover another set of basic editing features: searching, replacing text, and commenting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Vim/Neovim continued</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;basics-of-vimneovim-continued&#34;&gt;Basics of Vim/Neovim continued&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my previous post (&lt;a href=&#34;https://manbearpiet.com/posts/nvim/%29&#34;&gt;https://manbearpiet.com/posts/nvim/)&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned several modes and basics of editing in Vim/Neovim. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue the topic and show you how to use Tutor and help, as well as what you can do with Visual mode.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;help-and-tutor&#34;&gt;Help and Tutor&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I mentioned how to access and quit help articles in Vim/Neovim; these articles contain gems. There is even a tutoring tutorial program you can access with the Commandline Mode command using &lt;code&gt;:Tutor&lt;/code&gt;.&#xA;This program will guide you through the Neovim tutorial and will contain help with links.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Vim/Neovim</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;neowhat&#34;&gt;Neowhat?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was the end of May 2025. A friend and former colleague of mine sent me a link about a YouTuber called ThePrimeagen. In his videos, he featured some funny takes on tech news and had some sassy remarks, but what sparked my interest was his IDE. He used a terminal in which he was editing text, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t look like old-school Vi. It had rich support for languages, an uncluttered interface, and I never saw a mouse cursor. I was interested, so I viewed some more videos, and my Neovim journey began. I&amp;rsquo;ve a deep interest in how technology works, and I wanted a deeper understanding of how VSCode works and how it helps me with code editing. What better way than to check out the competition? This, plus a desire to become more able with editors like Vi, made it a clear choice to invest time to better understand this editor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signing your JWTs for your GitHub Apps using Azure KeyVault</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/signing-jwt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 12:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/signing-jwt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-apps&#34;&gt;GitHub Apps&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a previous post about GitHub Apps, I demonstrated how to use a PowerShell module to create your JWTs and interact with GitHub&amp;rsquo;s REST APIs. I don&amp;rsquo;t like storing the private key on the server, so in this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll show you how to use Azure Key Vault&amp;rsquo;s signing API to sign your JWT.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We want to get the same results, but without the private key on our host locally.&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://manbearpiet.github.io/images/github-apps/content.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Getting content with a GitHub App&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automating GitHub operations using GitHub Apps</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/githubapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/githubapp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-apps&#34;&gt;GitHub Apps&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the company I work at, InSpark, we had a use case for automating our operations on the GitHub platform. We needed to perform automated actions in a headless fashion, so an external process on Azure should be able to call the GitHub Platform and perform some actions. To do so, I learned about GitHub Apps, which enable me to perform actions from a script. In this blog, I will share what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned and how you can utilize a daemon application to automate actions on the GitHub platform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pester Crash course</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/pester/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/pester/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most developers reach a point where they can fluently write code in their language of choice. As features are added and the codebase expands, a critical question arises: do these changes break existing functionality? Do they work as expected? Testing frameworks like PowerShell&amp;rsquo;s Pester are designed to address these concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I will give you an overview of what Pester is, how you can write your own tests, how you need to structure them, and what value it can bring to your development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to work with errors in PowerShell</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/powershellerrors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 20:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/powershellerrors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my career, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen many different approaches to errors, all meant to address them.&#xA;However, none of these approaches provided a complete solution.&#xA;Either everything is dumped without a specific error, the script/function continues while it should error, or the wrong keywords are used, like &lt;strong&gt;break&lt;/strong&gt;.&#xA;Code with proper error handling is more reliable, easier to maintain, and makes it easier to understand what is happening.&#xA;In this blog, I will share what I have learned on how to create errors, how to handle errors, and what not to do.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete your resource groups and resource parameter values like Azure PowerShell</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azureargumentcompleters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azureargumentcompleters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I was busy with some module development, and I was wondering how the user experience could be more user-friendly.  When you use the Azure PowerShell modules you get nice autocompletion on resource groups and resources, so I was wondering if I could give the same comfort to my module and script users.&#xA;With this blog post I will show you, how I implement Azure PowerShell their argument completers, to give users of my scripts and modules this same experience with my parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Necromancing my blog</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/necromancing-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 12:47:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/necromancing-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-to-blog-again&#34;&gt;Starting to blog again&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last few years have been great for me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend and I bought a house 🏡, and we&amp;rsquo;ve done all sorts of DIY I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t dream of being able to.&#xA;I learned it&amp;rsquo;s great fun to do because you can immediately see/bear the the fruits of your work.&#xA;It was tiring, which was one of the reasons I didn&amp;rsquo;t pursue blogging anymore.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had success with my team, I started a new team with a valued colleague of mine, primarily focused on Deployment and Automation 🚀 (DNA).&#xA;This was a large step from the usual break/fix day to day of my previous team, although we were mostly involved in building new solutions.&#xA;So, more PowerShell, Bicep, Azure DevOps, and GitHub for us now, although I see more and more cool stuff coming from our Managed Services team, I could learn a lot from them. Our DNA-team is growing and we&amp;rsquo;ve some new challenges we want to overcome, and goals and we want to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Azure Policy to configure your resources</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/applying-guest-configuration-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 08:07:31 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/applying-guest-configuration-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;azure-policy-as-a-configuration-engine&#34;&gt;Azure Policy as a configuration engine?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://manbearpiet.github.io/images/applying-guest-config/feature.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Azure Policy&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xA; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;azure-policy-guest-configuration&#34;&gt;Azure Policy Guest Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a previous blog, I showed how to audit your GPO-contained settings&#xA;inside Azure VM&amp;rsquo;s using Azure Policy Guest Configuration. The packaging process&#xA;is a bit too much for some, and in some cases, you only need to perform a few&#xA;configuration settings. Luckily there are some settings you can already&#xA;configure with built-in policies. In this blog, I will show you what Azure&#xA;Policies are and how they are assigned. When you&amp;rsquo;ve read this post, you&amp;rsquo;ll be&#xA;able to assign Azure Policies to configure the state in your Azure environment and&#xA;your Virtual Machines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deliver your apps using Azure Front Door</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azurefrontdoor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 19:31:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azurefrontdoor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;azure-front-door&#34;&gt;Azure Front Door&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://manbearpiet.github.io/images/front-door/feature.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;HTTP Settings&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xA; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Frequently I speak to cloud admins and consultants who&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Azure Front Door, but are not sure about what it does or havent interacted with it. I have some experience deploying and managing Front Door instances of customers. Most heard comment is: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a thing that does something with application delivery, right?&amp;rdquo;. In the near future I want pursue on the AZ-700 certification, so I thought a win-win in blogging about! With this blog I want to show what Azure Front Door is, what the components are and make sure to mention a few gotcha&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auditing GPOs with Azure Guest Configuration Policy</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/guest-configuration-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 08:07:31 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/guest-configuration-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;os-hardening-security-auditing&#34;&gt;OS-hardening security auditing&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;What?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wanted to check compliance of a security baseline on Azure without first applying it via DSC. My primary goal was to check out how to validate our own internal security controls without using GPO&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Group Policy Objects are frequently used within a windows server domain to push settings, like security controls, and validate/reapply them to prevent configuration drift. My challenge was how to audit these settings, while knowing some customers also use Demilitarized Zones (DMZ&amp;rsquo;s) in Azure. Servers which reside in this network segment are exposed so they are not joined to the domain. But especially these servers do need to be checked on security controls. So there we have our puzzle. How to audit virtual machines on Azure for custom security configurations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Start a blog!</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 10:19:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;blog-blarg-blorg&#34;&gt;Blog! Blarg! Blorg!?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I have decent&amp;rsquo;ish ideas to solve challenges faced on the Microsoft Azure cloud, using Azure DevOps or with PowerShell.&#xA;If there&amp;rsquo;s code involved with solving these problems, that code tends to disappear in a folder I&amp;rsquo;ve accordingly named &lt;code&gt;Trash&lt;/code&gt;.&#xA;I frequently hear from colleagues and read tweets of people struggling with the same challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This blog will mostly feature my noobish take on challenges with these topics.&#xA;By writing this blog I hope to improve my webdev and writing skills, but mostly try to help readers facing earlier mentioned challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
