<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Manbearpiet</title>
    <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Manbearpiet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 22:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://manbearpiet.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using Azure Policy to audit and remediate your resources</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/applying-guest-configuration-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 22:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/applying-guest-configuration-policy/</guid>
      <description>Azure Policy as a configuration engine?  Azure Policy Guest Configuration In a previous blog, I showed how to audit your GPO-contained settings inside Azure VM&amp;rsquo;s using Azure Policy Guest Configuration. The packaging process is a bit too much for some, and in some cases, you only need to perform a few configuration settings. Luckily there are some settings you can already configure with built-in policies. In this blog, I will show you what Azure Policies are and how they are assigned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deliver your apps using Azure Front Door</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azurefrontdoor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 19:31:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/azurefrontdoor/</guid>
      <description>Azure Front Door  Frequently I speak to cloud admins and consultants who&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Azure Front Door, but are not sure about what it does or havent interacted with it. I have some experience deploying and managing Front Door instances of customers. Most heard comment is: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a thing that does something with application delivery, right?&amp;rdquo;. In the near future I want pursue on the AZ-700 certification, so I thought a win-win in blogging about!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auditing GPOs with Azure Guest Configuration Policy</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/guest-configuration-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 08:07:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/guest-configuration-policy/</guid>
      <description>OS-hardening security auditing What? I wanted to check compliance of a security baseline on Azure without first applying it via DSC. My primary goal was to check out how to validate our own internal security controls without using GPO&amp;rsquo;s.
Group Policy Objects are frequently used within a windows server domain to push settings, like security controls, and validate/reapply them to prevent configuration drift. My challenge was how to audit these settings, while knowing some customers also use Demilitarized Zones (DMZ&amp;rsquo;s) in Azure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Start a blog!</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 10:19:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Blog! Blarg! Blorg!? Why? Sometimes I have decent&amp;rsquo;ish ideas to solve challenges faced on the Microsoft Azure cloud, using Azure DevOps or with PowerShell. If there&amp;rsquo;s code involved with solving these problems, that code tends to disappear in a folder I&amp;rsquo;ve accordingly named Trash. I frequently hear from colleagues and read tweets of people struggling with the same challenges.
This blog will mostly feature my noobish take on challenges with these topics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>About me I&amp;rsquo;m 30 years old, working at InSpark at the Azure Infrastructure Engineering team. I&amp;rsquo;m mostly focused on Azure, deployment and automation. I have specific area of expertise, more allround. Aside from day to day operations and changes, I&amp;rsquo;m also developing at an internal team which builds management and deployment tooling for our colleagues.
My personal tech focus for 2021 is primairly on a few topics:
 &amp;lsquo;Mastering&amp;rsquo; safe and reliable application delivery on Azure, using Azure Front Door, API-Management, CDN etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
