<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neovim on Azure and DevOops</title>
    <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/tags/neovim/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Neovim on Azure and DevOops</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Christian Piet (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://manbearpiet.github.io/tags/neovim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Other Neovim editing basics</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;searching-replacing-and-commenting-in-neovim&#34;&gt;Searching, replacing, and commenting in Neovim&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my previous posts, I covered the basics of navigating Neovim and editing text. While moving around words, lines, or paragraphs in &lt;code&gt;Normal&lt;/code&gt; mode and selecting text with &lt;code&gt;Visual&lt;/code&gt; mode, it works swiftly to navigate around text; sometimes, you need to look for something specific one or multiple times. In this post, I will cover another set of basic editing features: searching, replacing text, and commenting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Vim/Neovim continued</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim-continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;basics-of-vimneovim-continued&#34;&gt;Basics of Vim/Neovim continued&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my previous post (&lt;a href=&#34;https://manbearpiet.com/posts/nvim/%29&#34;&gt;https://manbearpiet.com/posts/nvim/)&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned several modes and basics of editing in Vim/Neovim. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue the topic and show you how to use Tutor and help, as well as what you can do with Visual mode.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;help-and-tutor&#34;&gt;Help and Tutor&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I mentioned how to access and quit help articles in Vim/Neovim; these articles contain gems. There is even a tutoring tutorial program you can access with the Commandline Mode command using &lt;code&gt;:Tutor&lt;/code&gt;.&#xA;This program will guide you through the Neovim tutorial and will contain help with links.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Vim/Neovim</title>
      <link>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://manbearpiet.github.io/posts/nvim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;neowhat&#34;&gt;Neowhat?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was the end of May 2025. A friend and former colleague of mine sent me a link about a YouTuber called ThePrimeagen. In his videos, he featured some funny takes on tech news and had some sassy remarks, but what sparked my interest was his IDE. He used a terminal in which he was editing text, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t look like old-school Vi. It had rich support for languages, an uncluttered interface, and I never saw a mouse cursor. I was interested, so I viewed some more videos, and my Neovim journey began. I&amp;rsquo;ve a deep interest in how technology works, and I wanted a deeper understanding of how VSCode works and how it helps me with code editing. What better way than to check out the competition? This, plus a desire to become more able with editors like Vi, made it a clear choice to invest time to better understand this editor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
